Guide to the New-York Historical Society General Correspondence 1805-2024 (bulk, 1805-1982) NYHS-RG 2
New-York Historical Society
- Series III. General Correspondence, 1805-1908; 28.04 Linear feet in 66 boxes and 6 oversize folders
  - Correspondence. 1888 April (Box 31, Folder 10)
    Includes April 2 acceptance by Chevalier Ernst von Hesse-Wartegg of election to Foreign Corresponding member, asserting the high reputation in Europe of N-YHS as "one of the oldest and most distinguished scientific societies of the New World."
  - Correspondence. 1888 May (Box 31, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence. 1888 June (Box 32, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence. 1888 July (Box 32, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence. 1888 August-September (Box 32, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence. 1888 October (Box 32, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence. 1888 November (Box 32, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence. 1888 December (Box 32, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence. 1888-1889. Acquisitions of The Whig (Box 32, Folder 7)
    Includes December 1888 to July 1889 series of correspondence tracing the N-YHS acquisition of the office files of The Whig newspaper (established 1824, Richmond, Virginia): arrangements with editor Abner Wentworth Clopton Nowlin, funding solicitation drafts, letters accompanying N-YHS member contributions to the purchase fund, newspaper clippings, and reference inquiries.
  - Register of Correspondence. 1889 (Box 32, Folder 8)
    Frequent and notable correspondents include Matilda O. Abbey, Clarence W. Bowen, George S. Boutwell, Charles G. Barney, Hugh J. Grant, Charlton Thomas Lewis, Ezekial Wilson Mundy, F.S. Tallmadge, and organizations American Antiquarian Society, International Exhibition of 1892, Oneida Historical Society, and [United States] Biographical and Genealogical Society.
  - Correspondence. 1889 January 1-15 (Box 32, Folder 9)
    Includes January 7 letter from George West Van Sicle, secretary of the Holland Society of New York, suggesting N-YHS pursue a new building to accommodate both organizations; and series of reference inquiries and research reports from John Parkam on Richard Phillips (1716-1803).
  - Correspondence. 1889 January 16-31 (Box 32, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence. 1889 Feburary (Box 32, Folder 11)
    Includes February 16 letter introducing the Geological Society of America and seeking advice on the formulation of their publication plan, from secretary W.J. McGee.
  - Correspondence. 1889 March (Box 32, Folder 12)
    Includes March 8 circular (No. 214) issued by Massachusetts House of Representatives, reporting on Committee of Printing investigation into the publication process for the Province Laws, and requesting discontinuation based on high costs and inefficiency.
  - Correspondence. 1889 April (Box 33, Folder 1)
    Includes April 6 invoice for show cases provided by cabinet manufacturer John Bank; various correspondence surrounding events celebrating the centennial of the George Washington inauguration.
  - Correspondence. 1889 May (Box 33, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence. 1889 June (Box 33, Folder 3)
    Includes June 19 official circular from the National Library of Buenos Aires announcing governmental decree that they handle publication exchange services.
  - Correspondence. 1889 July-August (Box 33, Folder 4)
    Includes July 17 invitation for N-YHS president John A. King from New York City mayor Hugh J. Grant to join conference considering an international exposition to be held in the city in 1892, as well as King's response and commentary; two newspaper clippings dated August 3 and August 8 of letters to the editor of The Evening Post, both from anonymous women, complaining about the formal red-tape and lack of hospitality at N-YHS in regards to visitors.
  - Correspondence. 1889 September (Box 33, Folder 5)
    Includes September 6 letter regarding the incidents recounted in August letters to the editor of the Evening Post, from George P. Rowell, a member who provided the visitor card to one of the women and who seeks clarification on N-YHS policies.
  - Correspondence. 1889 October (Box 33, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence. 1889 November (Box 33, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence. 1889 December (Box 33, Folder 8)
  - Register of Correspondence. 1890 (Box 34, Folder 1)
    Frequent or notable corresponents include William K. Ackerman, John Bigelow, Charles William Bowen, Benjamin Franklin Stevens, and Wisconsin Historical Society.
  - Correspondence. 1890 January (Box 34, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence. 1890 February (Box 34, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence. 1890 March (Box 34, Folder 4)
    Includes letter from explorer Carl Sofus Lumholtz soliciting funding for his proposed explorations of the Sierra Madre and surrounding regions; attached are series of typescripts of letters of response and recommendations addressed to him from Alexander Agassiz of Museum of Comparative Zoology, F.W. Putnam of Peabody Museum at Harvard, Dr. D.G. Brinton of University of Pennsylvania, and other figures in the field.
  - Correspondence. 1890 April (Box 34, Folder 5)
    Includes April 17 letter from retired architect Alex J. Davis following up his recommendations "for a speedy erection of a more capacious receptacle for the collections of the Society," with attached notes by N-YHS president John A. King (see also: July-August 1890 folder for follow-up); circular on proposed monument to the Seneca chief Red Jacket, notated by sender Harriet Maywell Converse on April 28.
  - Correspondence. 1890 May (Box 34, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence. 1890 June (Box 34, Folder 7)
    Includes June 12 legal document relating to the bequest of Mary Rogers.
  - Correspondence. 1890 July-August (Box 34, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence. 1890 September (Box 34, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence. 1890 October (Box 34, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence. 1890 November (Box 34, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence. 1890 December (Box 34, Folder 12)
  - Register of Correspondence. 1891 (Box 35, Folder 1)
    General and notable correspondents include Samuel Putnam Avery, Silas Farmer, Charles R. Hildeburn, Howard L. Osgood, L. Ogilvy, A.C. Peale, and Charles H. Winfield.
  - Correspondence. 1891 January 1-15 (Box 35, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence. 1891 January 16-31 (Box 35, Folder 3)
    Includes January 21 letter from John B. and Marie A. Shipley recruiting N-YHS funding and participation in the establishment of a National Historical Museum in Chicago "for putting the historical truth connected with the discovery and colonization of this country into an objective and solid shape;" press clippings of the Shipleys' lectures and other activities.
  - Correspondence. 1891 February (Box 35, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence. 1891 March 1-15 (Box 35, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence. 1891 March 16-31 (Box 35, Folder 6)
    Includes two copies of letters from Oscar W. Collet of Missouri Historical Society contesting the acquisition of books from the library of Bishop Robertson; the second letter indicates that N-YHS was offended by his inquiry and execution.
  - Correspondence. 1891 April (Box 35, Folder 7)
    Includes April 10 inquiry from Department of the Interior regarding the research value of public documents, in light of Congress's recent reassessment of their publication and distribution.
  - Correspondence. 1891 May 1-15 (Box 35, Folder 8)
    Includes May 5 proposal by member Charles E. Moldenke to re-catalog the Abbott Collection, as the current one is "not only quite antiquated, but in many points absolutely wrong."
  - Correspondence. 1891 May 16-31 (Box 35, Folder 9)
    Includes May 24 genealogical inquiry from Henry T. Brooke with extensive summary of his family history.
  - Correspondence. 1891 May. Fiftieth St. Astoria Ferry and Central Park Railroad Company. Oversize (Box OS-1, Folder 15)
    Includes April-May materials relating to the proposed construction of a railroad across Central Park along several by-ways including 79th Street, where N-YHS held property: color map, circular, official inquiry, and property owner consent form.
  - Correspondence. 1891 June (Box 35, Folder 10)
    Includes June 18 reference inquiry from Herbert H. Crain detailing his efforts to trace the family tree of William and Jonathan Lawrence of England.
  - Correspondence. 1891 July-August (Box 35, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence. 1891 September-October (Box 35, Folder 12)
    Includes September 10 letter from A.D. Wales of Binghampton contesting a news item alleging a Rensselaer County house the oldest dwelling in the United States, which he believes is pre-dated by Saugerties house belonging to the DeWitt family; October 1 letter from Julius Goebel accompanying a flyer for the October 4 German Day celebration at Music Hall, commemorating the landing of the first German immigrants on American soil.
  - Correspondence. 1891 November (Box 35, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence. 1891 December 1-15 (Box 35, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence. 1891 December 16-31 (Box 35, Folder 15)
  - Register of Correspondence. 1892 (Box 36, Folder 1)
    Frequent or notable correspondents include A.W. Elson, Worthington C. Ford, Charles Folsom, and the United States Geological Survey.
  - Correspondence. 1892 January 1-15 (Box 36, Folder 2)
    Includes January 15 letter from William R. Steward seeking N-YHS cooperation in the erection of the Washington Square arch, describing monument design and intentions (see also: 1892 June folder).
  - Correspondence. 1892 January 16-31 (Box 36, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence. 1892 February (Box 36, Folder 4)
    Includes documents relating to the manuscripts, scrapbooks, and ephemera bequest of Thomas F. Devoe.
  - Correspondence. 1892 March (Box 36, Folder 5)
    Includes March 14 loan request for N-YHS Egyptian wheel holding, to display at the World's Columbian Exposition in Chicago (several further requests for this event occur throughout 1892 correspondence); early design for Grant's Tomb.
  - Correspondence. 1892 April 1-15 (Box 36, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence. 1892 April 16-30 (Box 36, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence. 1892 May (Box 36, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence. 1892 June (Box 36, Folder 9)
    Includes June 24 letter from Commissioner General S.B. Luce from the U.S. Commission for the Columbia Historical Exposition in Madrid, accompanying preliminary edition of circular outlining curation and publication activity and goals for the event.
  - Correspondence. 1892 July-August (Box 36, Folder 10)
    Includes program for the 116th Anniversary of the adoption of the Declaration of Independence at the Old Court House site in White Plains; and ten-page official document from Spanish Consulate in Paris (in Spanish).
  - Correspondence. 1892 September (Box 36, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence. 1892 October 1-20 (Box 36, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence. 1892 October 21-30 (Box 36, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence. 1892 November (Box 37, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence. 1892 December 1-15 (Box 37, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence. 1892 December 16-31 (Box 37, Folder 3)
  - Register of Correspondence. 1893 (Box 37, Folder 4)
    Frequent and notable correspondents include Ernest E. Coe, Henry T. Drowne, Irvington Lyon, William Nelson, Temple Prime, Gouverneur M. Smith, and John R. Williams.
  - Correspondence. 1893 January (Box 37, Folder 5)
    Includes legal documents relating to the bequests of Parthenia J. Norton and Tarrant Putnam; circular of the Committee of Retrospective Art for the 1893 World's Columbian Exposition; January 13 and 31 correspondence regarding Martha Lamb's bequest of her library and a portrait to N-YHS.
  - Correspondence. 1893 February (Box 37, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence. 1893 March (Box 37, Folder 7)
    Includes March 4 correspondence regarding Martha Lamb's bequest of her personal papers to N-YHS (see also: all 1893 files for follow-up inquries and comments).
  - Correspondence. 1893 April (Box 37, Folder 8)
    Includes April 10 complaint from W.E. Gregory about N-YHS's perceived indifference to the removal of the Old City Hall building.
  - Correspondence. 1893 May (Box 37, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence. 1893 June 1-15 (Box 37, Folder 10)
    Includes June 2 document regarding the bequest of Mary E. Bradish (see also: 1894 January folder).
  - Correspondence. 1893 June 16-30 (Box 37, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence. 1893 July-August (Box 38, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence. 1893 September-October (Box 38, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence. 1893 November (Box 38, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence. 1893 December (Box 38, Folder 4)
    Includes September 23 document regarding the bequest of James Francis Evans; and October 12 request for exchange from Anton Blomberg of the royal Academy of Belles Lettres, History and Antiquities of Stockholm.
  - Register of Correspondence. 1894 (Box 38, Folder 5)
    Frequent and notable correspondents include Charles D. Allen, Clarence W. Bowen, William W. Conway, William Nelson, George H. Sullivan, Issac F. Wood, Pennsylvania Historical Society and Smithsonian Institution.
  - Correspondence. 1894 January (Box 38, Folder 6)
    Includes January 22 letter from George Treadwell reporting on potential N-YHS Building fund donors and inviting Librarian Kelby to visit his gold mine operation in Nevada.
  - Correspondence. 1894 February (Box 38, Folder 7)
    Includes February 26 letter from Venezuelan historian Manuel Landaeta Rosales (in Spanish).
  - Correspondence. 1894 March 1-15 (Box 38, Folder 8)
    Includes newspaper clipping and accompanying March 22 letter from lawyer William Abbott on his campaign to name October 17 a state holiday, "Saratoga Day," to commemorate the Defeat of Burgoyne in the Revolutionary War.
  - Correspondence. 1894 March 16-31 (Box 38, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence. 1894 April (Box 39, Folder 1)
    Includes April 13 overview of early New York postal history by C.W. Ernst.
  - Correspondence. 1894 May (Box 39, Folder 2)
    Includes May 11 letter from John E. Davis, secretary of Sons of the Revolution of New York, accompanying circular on collection of articles owned and used by Abraham Lincoln for sale.
  - Correspondence. 1894 June (Box 39, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence. 1894 July-August (Box 39, Folder 4)
    Includes July 3 request from Joseph Cervierny to open fruit and candy stand serving temperance drinks on southwest corner of 77th Street and Eighth Avenue; decline from President John A. King.
  - Correspondence. 1894 September (Box 39, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence. 1894 October (Box 39, Folder 6)
    Includes blank application for membership in the Missouri Society of the Sons of the Revolution, attached to October 12 letter from its secretary Marshall DeLancey Haywood.
  - Correspondence. 1894 November (Box 39, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence. 1894 December (Box 39, Folder 8)
  - Register of Correspondence. 1895 (Box 40, Folder 1)
    Frequent and notable correspondents include Samuel Putnam Avery, William Ashmead Courtenay, William A. Clark, A.C. Goodell Jr., Charles Isham, George C. McWhorter, William Nelson, John Purdon, Abigail Seymour, and George H. Sullivan.
  - Correspondence. 1895 January 1-15 (Box 40, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence. 1895 January 16-31 (Box 40, Folder 3)
    Includes January 17 draft of letter from N-YHS librarian William Kelby to Phillip and Lloyd Phoenix, summarizing recent genealogical acquisitions and providing rare written example from this period of N-YHS pursuit of collection donors.
  - Correspondence. 1895 February (Box 40, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence. 1895 March 1-15 (Box 40, Folder 5)
    Includes undated argument from poet James Hooker Hamersley arguing for celebration of Sebastian Cabot as discoverer of America.
  - Correspondence. 1895 March 16-31 (Box 40, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence. 1895 April (Box 40, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence. 1895 May (Box 40, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence. 1895 June (Box 40, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence. 1895 July-August (Box 40, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence. 1895 September (Box 40, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence. 1895 October (Box 40, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence. 1895 November (Box 41, Folder 1)
    Includes November 10 New York World extract on Old Curiosity Shop run by Westminster Abbey on Front Street; November 20 letter from attorney Asa Bird Gardiner outlining his research for confirmation as to whether John Von Arsdale raised the American flag in place of the British flag in Battery Park on Evacuation Day, November 25, 1783.
  - Correspondence. 1895 December 1-15 (Box 41, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence. 1895 December 16-31 (Box 41, Folder 3)
  - Register of Correspondence. 1896 (Box 41, Folder 4)
    Frequent and notable correspondents include Mrs. William B. Beekman, Worthington C. Ford, Isaac J. Greenwood, I. Remsen Lane, George G. McWhorter, William Nelson, Walter G. Oakmen, and Abigail A. Seymour.
  - Correspondence. 1896 January 1-15 (Box 41, Folder 5)
    Includes January 7 letter from Smith E. Lane recounting his efforts to procure the collections of General Daniel E. Sickles, General William Tecumseh Sherman, and Cyrus W. Field for N-YHS.
  - Correspondence. 1896 January 16-31 (Box 41, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence. 1896 February 1-15 (Box 41, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence. 1896 February 16-28 (Box 41, Folder 8)
    Includes February 22 letter from F.D. Stone, Librarian of the Historical Society of Pennsylvania, introducing attached draft of resolution imploring the Committtee of Appropriations of the U.S. House of Representatives to allot funding for the publication of the Records and Papers of the Continental Congress.
  - Correspondence. 1896 March 1-15 (Box 41, Folder 9)
    Includes March 6 and March 12 letters from W.W. Kenly, secretary of the Associated Societies and Historical Museum Building of the City of New York organization, accompanying meeting invitation and drafted resolution for the assemblage of a Committee of Thirty to oversee the erection of a single building of offices, meeting rooms, library, and a museum for all Revolutionary and Colonial Relics held in New York.
  - Correspondence. 1896 March 16-31 (Box 41, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence. 1896 April (Box 41, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence. 1896 May (Box 41, Folder 12)
    Includes invitation to May 2 dedication of the new Columbia University site at Morningside Heights.
  - Correspondence. 1896 June (Box 42, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence. 1896 July (Box 42, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence. 1896 August-September (Box 42, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence. 1896 October 1-15 (Box 42, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence. 1896 October 16-31 (Box 42, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence. 1896 November (Box 42, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence. 1896 December 1-20 (Box 42, Folder 7)
    Includes November 25 inquiry from the Wright-Humason school on 76th street regarding usage of N-YHS lands for tennis courts and croquet grounds and December 12 refusal from N-YHS; announcement of opening and invitation to exhibit paintings at the Brooklyn Institute of Arts and Sciences.
  - Correspondence. 1896 December 21-31 (Box 42, Folder 8)
  - Register of Correspondence. 1897 (Box 42, Folder 9)
    Frequent and notable correspondents include Henry W. Bryant, Gherardi Davis, A.A. Folsom, Charles R. King, William Nelson, Stephen B. Weeks and Smithsonian Institution.
  - Correspondence. 1897 January 1-15 (Box 42, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence. 1897 January 16-31 (Box 42, Folder 11)
    Includes January 20 request from James Wright for N-YHS subscription funding of the second volume of his English Dialect Dictionary.
  - Correspondence. 1897 February (Box 42, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence. 1897 March (Box 43, Folder 1)
    Includes March 11 letter from W. Roy Stephenson of Winchester, Virginia, describing copper plate found on his property that may be a cipher used by the British armies of General Braddock during the Revolutionary War, accompanied by impression; March 20 letter from S.R. Laugley of the Smithsonian Institution requesting information for an international catalogue of Egyptian papyri and monuments, conceived by the Egyptian government and overseen by the Museum of Egyptian Antiquities.
  - Correspondence. 1897 April (Box 43, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence. 1897 May (Box 43, Folder 3)
    Includes May 6 inquiry into the status of new N-YHS building funding and construction from architect Edward Lippincott Tilton, with response from N-YHS secretary Edward F. De Lancey; Eadward Muybridge letter that discusses N-YHS's recent acquisition of Muybridge's San Francisco panorama via Daniel Parish.
  - Correspondence. 1897 June (Box 43, Folder 4)
    Includes June 12 letter from Seth Low, president of Columbia University, urging N-YHS to relocate to Morningside Heights and copy of June 22 response from N-YHS president John A. King.
  - Correspondence. 1897 July (Box 43, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence. 1897 August-September (Box 43, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence. 1897 October 1-20 (Box 43, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence. 1897 October 21-31 (Box 43, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence. 1897 November (Box 44, Folder 1)
    Includes undated meeting minutes extract from the boards of The New York Public Library, Astor, Lenox, and Tilden Foundations resolving that a committee be formed to consider and report on systematization under one administration (see also: 1898 March folder for copy of N-YHS meeting minutes extract declining the proposition).
  - Correspondence. 1897 December 1-20 (Box 44, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence. 1897 December 21-31 (Box 44, Folder 3)
    Includes letters regarding the $5,000 bequest of Henry Keteltas and transfer of Publication Fund shares of the late George Bancroft.
  - Register of Correspondence. 1898 (Box 44, Folder 4)
    Frequent and notable correspondents include W.F. Adams, H.W. Bryant, Joseph W. Barnwell, Henry H. Edes, A.A. Folsom, Charles Isham, William Nelson, Mary Perkins Quincy, and A.V.W. Van Vechten.
  - Correspondence. 1898 January (Box 44, Folder 5)
    Includes correspondence from executor William Allen Butler of Evert A. Duyckinck's N-YHS Publication Fund subscription and its bequeathed transfer to the New York Public Library, Astor, Lenox, and Tilden Foundations; correspondence from executors of Henry Keteltas estate; January 20 inquiry from illustrator Howard Pyle wishing to view scenes of the death of Fraser in Braddock's campaign.
  - Correspondence. 1898 February (Box 44, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence. 1898 March (Box 44, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence. 1898 April 1-15 (Box 44, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence. 1898 April 16-30 (Box 44, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence. 1898 May-June (Box 44, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence. 1898 July (Box 44, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence. 1898 August (Box 45, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence. 1898 September (Box 45, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence. 1898 October (Box 45, Folder 3)
    Includes October 24 inquiry from Commisioner of the U.S. Department of Education, studying the effects of the Civil War upon educational institutions, with formal survey.
  - Correspondence. 1898 November (Box 45, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence. 1898 December (Box 45, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence. Undated, [1898] (Box 45, Folder 6)
    Includes ticket and invitation to the Grolier Club; advertisement for the Soldiers' Musical Handkerchief, "the Most Unique of all War Souvenirs."
  - Correspondence. 1898-1899. Memoir of William Kelby (Box 45, Folder 7)
    Includes letters and other documents relating to the death of N-YHS librarian William Kelby and the N-YHS publication "Memoir of William Kelby," authored by John Austin Stevens (see also: 1898 files for correspondence between Stevens and Kelby's successor and brother Robert).
  - Register of Correspondence. 1899 (Box 45, Folder 8)